Guide to the New-York Historical Society Poster Collection 1790-2022 PR 55
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society poster collection
1790-2022
New-York Historical Society
PR 55
65 Linear feet
A large assemblage of posters (1790-2022), primarily 19th and 20th century American. This collection contains a range of posters that come from a variety of sources, and that are not part of other collections.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into 9 series based on subject. Of these, 4 series have separate, individual finding aids. This is due to the amount of material contained in this collection, as well as the piecemeal manner in which it has been processed over the years. Links to these individual finding aids can be found at the series level as well as here:
Series I. Art Posters 1890-1910
Series II. Circus Posters, 1838-1946
Series III. Civil War Posters 1861-1865
Series IV. World's Fair and Other Fairs Posters, 1854-1965
Series V. Political Posters, 1840-2008
Series VI. Motion Picture and Theater Posters, 1790-2022
Series VII. World War I Posters 1914-1920
Series VIII. World War II Posters 1941-1946
Series IX. Other Subjects, 1896-2021
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was compiled by New-York Historical Society over time from a variety of purchases and gifts.
Scope and Contents
An assemblage of posters, primarily 19th and 20th century American. This collection contains a range of posters that come from a variety of sources, and that are not part of other collections. Printing methods include woodcuts, lithography and photomechanical prints. The collection has been organized into 9 series based on subject. Individual finding aids have been prepared for Series I, III, VII, and VIII. Please refer to these individual finding aids (linked below) for more detailed information.
Series I. Art Posters (1890 to 1910) includes colorful advertisements for books, magazines and newspapers. Link to Art Posters finding aid.
Series II. Circus Posters (1838-1946) includes early advertisements for magicians, menageries, and human performers, as well as later full color circus posters.
Series III. Civil War Posters (1861-1865) contains recruiting posters, as well as those advertising auctions, drives, meetings, deserter lists, muster rolls, and various other announcements pertaining to the Civil War. Link to Civil War Posters finding aid.
Series IV. Fair Posters (1893-1965) includes posters from the New York World's Fair in 1939-1940 and in 1964-1965.
Series V. Political Posters (1840-2008) includes campaign posters from national and local elections.
Series VI. Motion Picture and Theater Posters (1790-2022) The bulk of the series dates from the late nineteenth to the early twentieth century. Earliest items in the collection are text playbills from the 1790s.
Series VII. World War I Posters (1917-1918) consists of posters, pictorial sheets and related ephemera used by governments and organizations during the first World War to persuade citizens to support the war and aid efforts. Approximately 1200 posters including Montgomery Flagg's famous "I Want You" drawing. Link to World War I Posters finding aid.
Series VIII. World War II Posters (1941-1946) posters related to various aspects of the United States' mobilization during World War II. Topics include recruitment, war bonds, general war support, production, and conservation. Link to World War II Posters finding aid.
Series IX. Miscellaneous Posters (1896-2021) topics include Women's activism/rights, Anti-war protests, Public health, AIDS, Transportation, and LGBTQ+ rights.
Lithographs.; Posters.; Prints (visual works)
- Series I. Art Posters, 1890-1910; 612 item(s) (approximately)
  Scope and Contents
  The Art Posters Series consists of approximately 612 striking prints used to advertise magazines, books, and newspapers. Notable artists include Edward Penfied and Joseph J. Gould. A separate inventory for this series is found through this link: Art Posters
- Series II. Circus Posters, 1838-1946
  Most of the posters in this series are individually cataloged in the library's catalog Bobcat in 2017. Researchers can use the partial call phrase "PR-055-02" to search for these items.
- Series III. Civil War Posters, 1861-1865; 466 item(s) (approximately)
  The Civil War Posters consist of a total of 466 items. Of this total, 275 are recruiting posters, 31 are posters advertising auctions, drives, meetings, and the remaining 160 items refer to deserter lists, muster rolls, and various other announcements and newspaper clippings pertaining to the Civil War.
  There is a separate inventory for the Civil War posters found at this link: Civil War Posters
- Series IV. World's Fair and Other Fairs Posters, 1854-1965; 40 item(s)
  The majority of posters are from the 1939 and 1964 World's Fairs held in New York City. Also includes posters from county and agricultural fairs.
  - Bristol Cattle Show and Fair!, 1854 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Poster published by Ontario County Times Power Press, Canandaigua, N.Y. The Bristol Agricultural and Mechanic's Association, Royal A. Andrews (President), sponsored the fair and the executive committee was comprised of Royal A. Andrews, William Thomas, W.G. Donielson, A. Jones, B.F. Hicks, and N.W. Randall. On back (in pencil), "November 29. 1951 William".
  - "Diploma" awarded by Fairfield County Agricultural Society, 1856 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Lith. of Sarony, Major & Knapp. Diploma awarded to Mr. J.M. Rose of Greenwich, Ct., by Tho. B. Butler, President, and A.H. Ryingcord(sp?), Secretary, as a Premium for fine collection of imported and fancy breeds of Fowls. On front(in pencil), "Sept. 27, 1927". On back(in pencil), "Gift of Mr. DeWitt M. Lockman. Sept. 7, 1934".
  - "Triumphs of the Age: Being a Memorial of the Sixteenth Exhibition of the Ohio Mechanic's Institute...", 1858 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Poster printed by Longley Brothers, Printers. Cincinnati, Ohio. Memorial written by R.E.H. Levering. Acquisition date(?) on front: Oct. 7/99.
  - Third Annual Exhibition and Fair of the Suffield Agricultural Society, 1861 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Poster published by Samuel Bowles & Company, Printers, Springfield. Officers of the Society were Gad Sheldon, David Rising, Nathan Clark, James B. Rose, H.S. Sheldon, F.P. Loomis, and Francis Sheldon. On back, stamped, "The New-York Historical Society Folk Arts Collection November 17, 1937".
  - East Granville Corners Cattle Show and Fair, 1862 (Folder FF 04-01)
    The officers of the Show and Fair were as follows: William Moore, President; Samuel T. Ellis, Marshal; Selvin Crosby, Ass't Marshal; J.M. Gibbons, Treasurer; and Ansel Clark, Secretary. Committees included ones for oxen, fancy matched cattle, sheep and swine, poultry, stallions, vegetables, fruits, and grains, fancy articles, and mechanical products. Stamped on back, "The New-York Historical Society Folk Arts Collection November 17, 1937".
  - "Our Daily Fare!" The Great Central Fair Newspaper, 1864 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Poster was printed by Henry B. Ashmead, Printer. The special subscription newspaper published daily during the continuance of The Great Central Fair held in Philadelphia was published by Geo. W. Childs, Philadelphia. On front (in pencil), "May 15/06".
  - Grand Charitable Fair and Presentation Festival in aid of the Home and School for the Maintenance and Education of the Destitute Children of our Soldiers and Sailors., 1866 (Folder FF 04-01)
    The Fair was held at the Public Hall, Corner of Broadway and 23rd Street. Presents, including 10,000 in U.S. Greenbacks and a country residence in Westchester, were awarded at the Grand Presentation Festival held at the Cooper Institute. Thomas & Co. were the managing directors. Special notice concerning the prize tickets on the back of poster.
  - 23d Annual Harden County Fair held on the grounds of the Society at Kenton, IA., 1889 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Poster (Sample Half Sheet No. 27) published by The Fair Publishing House Poster Print, Norwalk, Ohio. M.G. Botsford was president and A.L. Marshal was secretary of the Society.
  - Items from 1893 Chicago Worlds Fair, 1894 (Folder FF 04-02)
    Most of the items appear to be from an artfolio published by The White City Art Company of Chicago and Denver. The artfolio was issued weekly with four plates (80 in total were intended to be reproduced) and text by Stanley Wood, Esq. It was printed by The Lakeside Press, R.R. Donnelley & Sons, Co., Chicago. The images are as follows:
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. Mining and Electricity Buildings, from Transportation Building. 2. Golden Door of Transportation Building. 3. Manufactures Building, from Horticultural Hall. 4. View South East from The Illinois Building. 5. General View, from The Lake. 6. View North, from between Manufactures and Electricity Buildings. 7. Transportation Building, from Wooded Island. 8. The Water Gate. 9. Fire Boat and Agricultural Building. 10. Agricultural Building, from Colonnade. 11. Manufactures Building, from Casino. 12. Columbia Avenue in Manufactures Building. 13. MacMonnies Fountain, from South Terrace. 14. The Woman's Building. 15. Interior of Woman's Building.
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by A. Zeese & Co., Chi. 1. Peristyle and the Water Gate, from Grand Basin. (2 copies) 2. Government Building and Wooded Island. (2 copies) 3. West View of Manufactures Building. 4. Chicago Day. 5. The Administration Building, from the South East. 6. MacMonnies Fountain, from Grand Plaza. (2 copies)
    Reproductions published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. Main Entrance of Woman's Building. 2. View from Balcony of Woman's Building. 3. Rear View of MacMonnies Fountain. 4. MacMonnies Fountain, from the South 5. Statue of Columbus, East Entrance Administration Building. 6. Statue of Industry. 7. The White City at Midnight. 8. East Façade of Machinery Hall. 9. Manufactures and Electricity Buildings, from Squatter's Hut. 10. Statue of Plenty. 11. South Entrance of Mining Building. 12. German Government Building. 13. The Immense Crowd. 14. Bird's-Eye View of State Buildings at the White City.
    Other reproductions 1. Statue of Cowboy 2. Group of Statuary, Transportation Building 3. Statue of Indian Scout 4. North Façade of Mining Building
    The other items in the folder are: 1. Photograph by C.D. Arnold (official photographer) of Interior of Manufactures and Liberal Arts Building.
    2. 9 illustrations (by E. Eldon Deane, M. Kenyan(?), del., and William LeBaron Jenney, architect, and unsigned) and long captions of The Woman's Building, The Fish and Fisheries Building, The Agricultural Building, The Mines and Mining Building, The Electrical Building, The Horticulural Building, The Transportation Building, The Machinery Hall, and The Administration Building.
    3. Unsigned illustration of Bird's Eye View of the Worlds Columbian Exposition, Showing Designs and Grouping of all Buildings Now Determined Upon.
  - Items from Chicago Worlds Fair, 1894 (Folder FF 04-03)
    All items are reprouctions that appear to be from an artfolio published by The White City Art Company of Chicago and Denver. The artfolio was issued weekly with four plates (80 in total were intended to be reproduced) and text by Stanley Wood, Esq. It was printed by The Lakeside Press, R.R. Donnelley & Sons, Co., Chicago. The images are as follows:
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. Statue of the Republic and Peristyle. 2. The Caravels from the Bridge. 3. View North West, from Manufactures Building. 4. La Rabida, from South West Side. 5. Electricity Building, Looking South West. 6. North Lagoon, from Mining Building. 7. View of North Lagoon, Art Palace and State Buildings. 8. North Front of Agricultural Building. 9. Horticultural Building, from Wooded Island. 10. Administration Building, Looking North East. 11. Looking South between Electricity and Mining Buildings. 12. View South East from The Illinois Building. 13. Peristyle from Lake. 14. Statue of Liberty. 15. View of the Lake Front. 16. General View, from The Lake 17. Lake Front, from Manufactures Building. 18. State Buildings of Massachusetts, New York and Pennsylvania. 19. The Obelisk and Grand Vista North from Colonnade. 20. South Façade of Art Palace. 21. Choral Hall, from Wooded Island. 22. Agricultural Building, from Colonnade. 23. Interior of Choral Hall. 24. Fire Boat and Agricultural Building. 25. Machinery Hall, from Colonnade. 26. Machinery Hall, from North East. 27. Looking North between Mines and Electricity Buildings.
    Reproductions copyrighted by W.H. Jackson and published by A. Zeese & Co., Chi. 1. The Administration Building, from the South East. 2. The Fisheries Building.
    Reproductions published by Franklin Co., Chi. 1. South Colonnade. 2. Interior of Electricity Building. 3. North West Corner Agricultural Building. 4. Main Entrance of Agricultural Building. 5. Ferris Wheel, and Bird's-Eye View of Midway. 6. Court of Honor, Looking West. 7. Court of Honor, Looking East. 8. Panorama of State Buildings, from North East. 9. Details of Main Entrance of Art Palace. 10. Administration Building at Night, from Electricity Building. 11. Electricity Building and Fountain. 12. East Entrance Horticultural Building. 13. Midway Plaisance, Looking West.
    Other reproductions 1. View North from Colonnade. 2. Administration Building, from Agricultural Building. 3. Agricultural Building at Night, from North West.
  - Westchester County Fair Horse and Cattle Show at White Plains, N.Y., 1899 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Poster published by Hennegan & Co., Cincinnati. James Hopkins, President, and E.B. Long, Secretary, for the Fair committee. The Great Baby show, the Japanese Day Fireworks, and the Parisian Dog Hippodrome were a few of the entertainment acts. On front (in pencil), "E.B. Child Feb. 1946". More information about the fair is published on the reverse side.
  - Your Town That Village of 8,000,000 People, 1938 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Copyright by Robert K. Straus, Councilman, and drawn by Fred Cooper. Features a pictorial map of New York City advertising the Robert K. Straus' radio show on Monday nights at 8:30 on WHN at 1010 on the dial.
  - The New York Official World's Fair Pictorial Map, 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Created by Tony Sarg and published by Tony Sarg Publications, Inc., N.Y. Printed in U.S.A. by Pace Press, Inc., N.Y.C. Front cover features Trylon and Perisphere. Map lists alphabetically exhibits and amusement area. On back, places to eat at the Fair. 4 pages.
  - The New York Official World's Fair Pictorial Map, 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Several page pamphlet created by Tony Sarg and published by Tony Sarg Publications, Inc., N.Y. Printed in U.S.A. by Pace Press, Inc., N.Y.C. Front cover features Trylon and Perisphere. The pamphlet has a large map and several detailed maps of each area of the fairgrounds. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, Oct. 14, 1939.
  - Matted Tony Sarg Pictorial Map of New York World's Fair, 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Published by Tony Sarg Publications, Inc., New York, N.Y. This pictorial map is unfolded and matted.
  - "Only 2,075 Miles To Go!", 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Copyright, 1939, National Geographic Society. Printed in U.S.A. Dufaycolor Photograph by Luis Marden. Features a young man, holding a New York sign, hitchhiking on a bridge that includes signage: "2075 miles to George Washington Bridge, Holland Tunnel, Lincoln Tunnel". The caption explains, "These signs on the International Bridge at Laredo, Texas, were provided by the New York World's Fair."
  - Pamphlet on Ford Building at the New York World's Fair (Folder FF 04-04)
    The front cover features the Ford Building and the Road of Tomorrow. The back cover features five car models produced by Ford. On the inside pages is printed The New Yorker's Map of the World of Tomorrow together with an index to its principal features, revised for issue of July 8, 1939, created by Carl Rose.
  - New York World's Fair certificate of appointment to Advisory Committee on Women's Participation, 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    The certificate features the Trylon and Perisphere and appointed Mrs. Ripley Hitchcock to the committee. It was signed by the President, Grover Whalen, and sceretary.
  - New York World's Fair certificate of appointment to Advisory Committee on Patriotic and Historical Societies, 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    The certificate features the Trylon and Perisphere and appointed Mr. Alexander Wall to the committee. It was signed by the President, Grover Whalen, and sceretary.
  - New York World's Fair Kerchief Designs, c.1939 (Folder FF 04-05)
    18 Kerchief designs for the World's Fair. NYHS also owns many of the kerchiefs based on these designs.
    1. Scarlett O'Hara. Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 2. Scarlett-Rhett. Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 3. New York World's Fair. (Featuring significant buildings and Trylon and Perisphere). Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by the NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 4. New York World's Fair. (Featuring areas of interest and Trylon and Perisphere). Designed by Eaton and Royal Studios and copyrighted by the NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 5. World's Fair Music Hall. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 6. Trylon and Perisphere. Designed by Eaton (M. Eaton & Co., New York) and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 7. New York World's Fair Horticultural Exhibit. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 8. Aviation Building, Health Science Medical and Education Building, Contemporary Art Building, and Maritime Building. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 9. Rockefeller Center New York. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 10. Boston Monuments. (Including Faneuil Hall, Old State House, Old North Church). Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 11. Little Church around the Corner. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 12. New York World's Fair 1939: The World of Tomorrow. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 13. "Americana" Patriotic Design in Red, White, and Blue, with Eagle. Acquisition date (?) on back, Aug. 13, 1941. In pencil, on back, "From Edgar C. Hywanth…" 14. New York City Monuments. (Including Empire State Building, Metropolitan Museum). Designed by Eaton and D.W. Serrano Studio Designers, New York. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 15. Pictorial Map of Manhattan and How to get to World's Fair. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 16. New York Public Library (2 copies. One colored green and tan, one colored pink, blue, and green) Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 17. Statue of Liberty. Designed by Eaton. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941. 18. World's Fair Administration Building. Designed by Eaton and copyrighted by NYWF. Acquisition date(?) on back, Oct. 7, 1941.
  - The World's Fair of 1940 for Peace and Freedom...Opens May 11 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features bird's-eye view of the fairgrounds. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - Ford 1940 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features hood of car with Ford logo. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - For Peace and Freedom. The World's Fair New York...Opens May 11th, 1940 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features flags of the world. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - World's Fair New York 1940 for Peace and Freedom (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features Ford Building. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - The World's Fair of 1940 New York Opens May 11th (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster on illustration board hand done by E.P. Chrystie. Features monumental statue of George Washington. Acquisition date (?), in pencil, on back, February 27, 1952.
  - Visit International Centennial Stamp Exhibition, British Pavilion World's Fair, 1940 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster created by Bob Smith. Features the "Penny Black", the World's first postage stamp issued in 1840.
  - Peace and Freedom. World's Fair of 1940 in New York (Folder FF 04-04)
    2 copies. Poster was made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc. N.Y.C. Poster features Trylon and Perisphere and the Constitution Mall. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back of both copies, June 20, 1940.
  - World's Fair of 1940 in New York Announcement of Opening Day (Folder FF 04-04)
    Poster was made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. Opening day was May 11th and admission was 50 cents. Poster features flags of the World and a monumental statue. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, April 4, 1940. An attached cover letter from The World's Fair of 1940 in New York asks recepient to hang poster in library in an effort to bring more people to the Fair.
  - World's Fair of 1940 in New York Announcement of Opening Day (Folder FF 04-04)
    The poster was made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. and designed by Howard Scott. Features a patriotic older gentleman in hat and three-piece suit at the Fair. Opening day was May 11th and admission was 50 cents. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back, April 4, 1940.
  - "Go By All Means World's Fair in New York 1940" (Folder FF 04-04)
    2 copies. Poster made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. Poster created by S. Ekman. Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back of both copies, June 20, 1940.
  - "For Your Summer Vacation...World's Fair New York", 1939 (Folder FF 04-04)
    2 copies. Poster made in U.S.A. by Polygraphic Company of America, Inc., N.Y.C. Poster designed by Bob Smith with the tagline, "Travel America...See the World at the World's Fair in New York". Acquisition date(?), in pencil, on back of both copies, June 20, 1940.
  - Reproduction: "Country Fair" by John A. Woodside, 1824., 1940 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Reproduced print is an offset lithography by Rogers-Kellogg-Stillson of the original painting in the collection of Harry T. Peters. It is attached to the front of a greeting card from Harry T. Peters. On the back of the card, Peters explained that "Country Fair", depicting a country fair near the city of Philadelphia, is believed to be the first graphic record in America of a country fair. On back (in pencil), "Dec. 26, 1940".
  - "Perisphere, Melting into History", 1941 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Photograph and caption from the New York Journal and American, February 27, 1941. Features a dismantled Perisphere with the caption explaining that the salvaged metal would go to the Defense program.
  - Newspaper photograph of the steel skeletons of the Trylon and Perisphere, c. 1941 (Folder FF 04-04)
    Photograph and caption from a newspaper, undated.
  - Reprint: "Sights at the Fair Ground.", c. 1955 (Folder FF 04-01)
    Reprint of a 1888 Currier & Ives print. On front(in pencil) "#10472 (c.1955)" Stamped in many places "N.Y. Public Library Picture Collection". On back, a note on the Currier & Ives prints, "The Road ..."